Preliminary Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Memorabilia Collection,, 1850-2000 MVC0029.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Metals, Series 4
  - Sterling silver plate on pedestal presented to class of 1918 from class of 1917, circa 1917; Series 4 (Box 19, Item 1)
    Inscribed "Class of 1918 from Class of 1917"
  - Sterling silver trophy "The Optima Club of Mount Vernon Seminary", circa 1921; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 2)
    Inscribed: "Presented by The Optima Members of the Class of 1921 V. Phillips-Pres.- D. Kilbourne-Vice Pres. I. Robinson - Sec. J Campbell J. Carle N. Daniels E. Davidson M. Kalmus D. Lacy C. Lucking H. Phillips J. Schneider S. Smith B. Thompson"
  - Weighted sterling silver candlestick, 1923; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 4)
    Manufactured by Ellis Jacob Greenburg & Co., founded in 1850 in London (indicated by the hallmarks). The "y" hallmark is the hallmark of 1923.
  - Weighted sterling silver candlestick, 1923; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 5)
  - Cement loaded sterling silver "Alumnae Reunion Cup" trophy, circa 1925; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 4)
    Manufactured by Webster Company, founded in North Attleboro, MA in 1869.
    Inscribed "Alumnae Reunion Cup Presented by Jean Dean Cole Golden Jubilee 1925"
    "Class of 1881, Class of 1933, Class of 1886, Clas of 1888, Class of 1925, Class of 1926"
  - Sterling silver trophy "Scholarship Cup", circa 1927; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 3)
    Inscribed "Scholarship Cup Presented By Genevieve D. Stewart '27" "Awarded to Eileen Lafferty '27 Daisy Parsons '28 Marianne L. Stevenson '28 Flora Kaiser '30 Flora Kaiser '31 Katherine Cable '32 Marguerite Beach '33 Barbara Sincerbeaux '34 Amy Slade Hopkins '35 Helen Mar Tolen '36 Marianna Adair '37 Marjorie Mae Allen '38"
  - Silver plated pitcher given to class of 1928 from class of 1927, circa 1927; Series 4 (Box 22, Item 2)
    Manufactured by Wilcox S.P. Co. under the International Silver Company.
    Inscribed "Presented to the Class of 1928 by the Class of 1927"
  - Silver plated teapot given to class of 1927 from class of 1926, circa 1927; Series 4 (Box 22, Item 3)
    Manufactured by Wilcox Silver Plate Company in Meriden, CT.
    Inscribed "Presented to the Class of 1927 by the Class of 1926"
  - Silver plated trophy cup given to class of 1928 from class of 1927, circa 1927; Series 4 (Box 22, Item 1)
  - Sterling silver trophy "Mount Vernon Seminary Inter Class Swimming Meet Trophy", circa 1929; Series 4 (Box 20, Item 1)
    Inscribed "Mount Vernon Seminary Inter Class Swimming Meet Trophy Presented by Margaret G. Finley"
    " Won by White Class - 1929 Yellow Class - 1931 Yellow Class - 1932 Yellow Team - 1933 White Team - 1934 Yellow Team - 1935 Yellow Team - 1938 White Team - 1940 White Team - 1941 Yellow Team - 1942"
  - Silver commemorative bowl--gift from the class of 1934, Series 4 (Box 21, Item 2)
    An inscription on the bowl reads "To the Class of '35 and all succeeding Classes From the Class of '34"
    A stamp on the bottom of the piece with the word "sterling" identifies this as true silver.
  - Sterling silver large serving fork with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 17, Item 6)
    The hallmark on this piece (an "A" in the form of a hammer with the handle extending through the word "Stone" and crossing the "t")indicates that it was manufactured by Arthur Stone's silver production company. Stone's private company was in business in Massachusetts from 1901 until Stone's retirement in 1937.
    The small "H" next to the logo indicates that the pieces were manufactured between ca. 1938 and 1957, when the company was under the direction of Henry Heywood.
    see: http://www.925-1000.com/a_stone.html
  - 12 sterling silver salad forks with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 17, Item 1)
  - 12 sterling silver forks with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958 (Box 17, Item 2)
  - 9 sterling silver dessert forks with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 17, Item 3)
  - 12 sterling silver dinner forks with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 17, Item 4)
  - 4 sterling silver carving forks with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 17, Item 5)
  - 4 sterling silver miniature spoons with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 8)
  - Sterling silver small ladle with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958 (Box 18, Item 14)
  - 7 sterling silver spread knives with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 7)
  - 2 sterling silver pie servers "M.V.S." with monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 9)
  - 10 sterling silver tablespoons with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 6)
  - 10 sterling silver teaspoons with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 5)
  - 8 sterling silver coffee spoons with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 2)
  - Sterling silver flat spoon with curved top with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 11)
  - 7 sterling silver serving spoons with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 10)
  - Sterling silver iced tea spoon with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 12)
  - Sterling silver large serving spoon with "M.V.S." monogram, circa 1937-1958; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 13)
  - Sterling silver trophy cup "Mount Vernon Seminary Margaret Acheson Stuart Science Achievement Award", circa 1959; Series 4 (Box 19, Item 2)
    Inscribed: "Mount Vernon Seminary Margaret Acheson Stuart Science Achievement Award" "Mary Drew Preston 1959 Kaycee Hough, Carter Dunlop 1960 1961 Carol Ruth Cousins 1962 Suzanne Michele Spitz 1963 Virginia Darrell Nuessle 1964 Clara Blanche Capel 1965 Margaret McMillan Johnson 1966 Mary Fleming Heasty 1967 Vicki case 1968 Mary Preston Asher"
  - Sterling silver Good Housekeeping Award cup, 1959-1969; Series 4 (Box 21, Item 1)
    The following inscriptions are found on the object: "Good Housekeeping Award Presented by Olwen Lloyd Headmistress" "1959 Letty McDonald, Ann Collier Taylor" "1960 Rudi Borland, Ruthie Borland" "1961 Louise Bonnie Knickerbocker, Elisabeth Jane O'Leary" "1962 Kathleen Phillips Garson, Caroline Bowden Simpson" "1963 Pamela Bateman, Anne Jones Morton" "1964 Mary Linda DeButts, Carolyn Taft Knowlton" "1965 Helen Chatterly Fay, Barbara Lansing Collins" "1966 Nan Sherrill Lyles, Anne Dale Owen, Elsie Hall Taylor" "1967 Melinda Poole, Kimberly Watson" "1968 Elizabeth Pfaff, Barbara Quinn, Melinda Poole, Sharon Railing" "1969 Janet Brockett, Elizabeth Howell"
    The piece is stamped with the word "sterling" on the bottom, indicating that it is made of real silver.
  - Sterling silver citizenship award trophy bowl presented by the class of 1959, circa 1959; Series 4 (Box 19, Item 6)
    Manufactured by Samuel Kirk & Son (establisehd 1846 in Baltimore, MD) for Galt & Bro. (established 1802 in Washington, DC).
    Inscribed "Citizenship Award Presented By The Class of 1959" "1959 Nancy Barnes 1960 Chris Thomson 1961 Susan Myers Campbell 1962 Mary Catherine Patterson 1963 Cynthia Hardman Collins 1964 Tempe Dana Grant 1965 Carolyn Louise Keith 1966 Anne Olivia Owen 1967 Mary Evins, Carolyn Mercer 1968 Cynthia Beasley, Alexandra Gibson 1969 Florence Lehmann"
  - Sterling silver trophy cup "Progressus maximus fractus noster est", circa 1962; Series 4 (Box 19, Item 3)
    Manufactured by Boardman (established 1828 Hartford, CT).
    Inscribed: "The Riders 1962 Anne Jones Morton 1962 Anne Jones Morton 1962 Jennifer Bell 1964 Jennifer Bell 1965 Joan Westaway 1966 Gabrielle Egger 1967"
  - Sterling silver trophy plate "Mount Vernon Seminary Olwen LLoyd Mathematics Award", circa 1964; Series 4 (Box 19, Item 4)
    Inscribed: "Mount Vernon Seminary Olwen LLoyd Mathematics Award" "Betsy Wilson Leith 1964 Carol Lynn Hock 1965 Sheryl Lee Hehemann 1966 Sheryl Lee Hehemann 1967 Mary Preston Asher 1968 Sharon Railing 1969"
  - Pewter trophy cup "Mount Vernon College Bachelor of Arts Award in Public Affairs and Government", circa 1974; Series 4 (Box 26, Item 3)
    Made of Stieff Pewter (made of tin, antimony, and copper; no lead).
    Inscribed: "Mount Vernon College Bachelor of Arts Award in Pubilc Affairs and Government" "Nancy Lynne Hughes 1980 Leslie Braun 1981 Susan Wailes 1974 Ann Kerr Gulley 1975 Kimberly Smith 1976 Jean Newman 1977 Lisa Jonas 1978 Beverly McKittrick 1979 Lynne Hughes 1980 Patpicia Sessa 1981 Leslie Braun 1982"
  - Silver plate trophy cup "M.V.C. Jane Dally Memorial Father-Daughter Tennis Tournament 1976 First Place", circa 1976; Series 4 (Box 24, Item 1)
  - Silver plated small trophy plate, circa 1981; Series 4 (Box 28, Item 5)
    Inscribed "Alma Schmidt Peterson Award Mount Vernon College 1981"
  - Silver plated small trophy plate, circa 1981; Series 4 (Box 28, Item 4)
    Inscribed "Elsie Foerderer Scholad Mount Vernon College 1981"
  - Silver plated small trophy plate, circa 1981; Series 4 (Box 28, Item 3)
    Inscribed "Masako Kawasaki Wittner Scholar Mount Vernon College 1981"
  - Silver plated trophy cup on wooden stand, "Fesenmyer Music Award", circa 1984; Series 4 (Box 23, Item 2)
    Inscribed "Fesenmyer Music Award 1984/85 Diana Erkelens 1985/86 Pamela Wood 1986/87 Sigalit Avigdory 1987/88 Eri Iwasaki /90 Deborah James /91Dagney Faulk /92 Tracy Flax, Masako Yamada"
  - Silver plated trophy plate, circa 1986; Series 4 (Box 28, Item 2)
    Inscribed "Mount Vernon College Elsie Foerderer Alumna Scholar, Ingrid Horton, Convocation 1986"
  - Electroplated silver trophy cup "Mount Vernon College Tennis Classic", circa 1987; Series 4 (Box 25, Item 2)
    Inscribed: "1987 Ambassador Wilhelm Wachtmeister, Tom Jarriel 1988 James C. Miller III, Neil McGinness, Frank J. Fahrenkope Jr., Bruce Ellis 1990 William Webster, Michael Boskin"
  - Brass chandelier candlestick with crystal-like ornaments, undated; Series 4 (Box 29, Item 1)
  - Carved stone lamp finial, undated; Series 4 (Box 29, Item 3)
    Finial is broken into two pieces.
  - Pewter plate, undated; Series 4 (Box 26, Item 1)
    Decorated around the edges with a floral motif. Inscribed with "CRC" on bottom.
  - Sheffield plate ladle, undated; Series 4 (Box 23, Item 1)
    The hallmarks on this ladle include the letter G in a shield, the numbers 4 and 8 in circles, and four circle/hemispherical shapes forming a clover like shape.
  - Sheffield plate mesh dish on small stand, undated; Series 4 (Box 27, Item 1)
    The pinkish-orange color visible in various areas of the dish identifies it as Sheffield plate (layered combination of silver on top of copper). It is known that this piece was made in London because of a stamp on the bottom. There are two other stamps: one of a hand and one of a rectangle with the letters "BB" inside it.
  - Silver plated nickel silver plate on stand, undated; Series 4 (Box 28, Item 1)
    Inscribed "ECS" (?)
  - Silver plated repousee vase, undated; Series 4 (Box 27, Item 3)
  - Silver plated repousee vase, undated; Series 4 (Box 27, Item 4)
  - Silver plated small bowl, undated; Series 4 (Box 24, Item 3)
  - Silver plated small bowl, undated; Series 4 (Box 24, Item 4)
  - Silver plated tablespoon, undated; Series 4 (Box 29, Item 2)
    Inscribed "MV"
  - Sterling silver sugar tongs, undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Item 3)
    The tongs are decorated with a floral pattern on the handle and have bird-like claws for the tongs.
  - Sterling silver urn with lid, undated; Series 4 (Box 21, Item 3)
- Chasseriau Etchings, undated; Series 5
  This series contains 12 prints of subjects from Shakespeare's Othello. The original series of 18 etchings was created by French romantic artist Theodore Chasseriau in 1844. Multiple print editions were made of the etchings and prints continue to be popular. The prints in this collection are undated and there is no information as to their provenance.
  Theodore Chasseriau (b. September 20, 1819; d. October 8, 1856.) was a French Romantic painter who studied under Jean-Auguste Dominique Ingres starting at age 11. Ingres considered Chasseriau his protege and passed on the preference for drawing and modeling. Chasseriau separated from his mentor and began following the works of Eugene Delacroix an artist famous for his use of color. These two role models shaped Chasseriau's artistry allowing him to combine Classical and Romantic stylistic devices. Chasseriau was known in his time for historical scenes and portraits, murals in churches throughout Paris, and popularising Orientalism. Sources: Art Directory, Fine Art Online. 04 Jan. 2012. <//www.art-directory.info/fine-art/theodore-chasseriau-1819>. Nicholas Pioch. "Chasseriau, Theodore." WebMuseum Paris Online. 04 Jan. 2012. <//www.ibilio.org/wm/paint/auth/chasseriau/>.
  - Othello Plate 1, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Bent top right corner (Flat box 30)
    Artist
  - Othello Plate 2, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6; Bent top right corner and small indent in the top left border (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 3, undated; Series 5; Crease on the backside, center of the sheet; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 4, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Two indents in top left border (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 5, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm (Flat box 30)
    Bent top right and bottom right corners
  - Othello Plate 9, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Smudge on the left border below center. Mark on back, low center (ink?) (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 10, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Crease in the center of the right border (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 11, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Small brown stain on the back at bottom center. Small brown stain on the back at right center. (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 13, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Linear indentation on back at bottom left border. Indentation on front bottom right border. (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 14, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Particle on middle left border (yellow/tan, adhesive?) (Flat box 30)
  - Othello Plate 15, undated; Series 5; Image: 29.6 cm x 21.8 cm Block: 30.5 cm x 22.2 cm Sheet: 40.6 cm x 28.6 cm; Brown stain on back at top right. Back side spotted with various colors and materials. (Flat box 30)